[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
boom all right uh so it looks like we're
going to have an intimate
uh stowa this evening uh we should
engender some good conversations
uh i'm peter limberg the steward of the
stoa and the stow is a place for us to
cohere and
dialogue about what matters most at the
knight's edge
of this very moment and today we have
william fariello uh and he could uh um
yeah okay good i got the salute and uh
today he's going to talk about his new
book
and we have a special mc my buddy
michael
trombley mike is a phd candidate
in the philosophy in philosophy at
queen's university he studies epictetus
and he's a practitioner in jiu-jitsu i
think he's a black belt
and he has some mma fights on him it's
up to you if you want to google it
or look it on youtube um
and uh yeah so i'm going to hand it to
mike right now and mike's going to
introduce uh
bill and then uh we're going to talk and
then he's going to talk about the
question in a protocol so
that being said i will allow mike to
unmute himself and take him in
great so hi everyone um excited to be
here excited to do this
and talk about this new exciting book
with a great speaker
um so the way this is gonna work as far
as i understand is i'm gonna start off
with a couple questions
with william we're gonna have a back and
forth uh after the
after that we'll open it up to the chat
so if anyone has any questions
during uh bill and i's back and forth
just write those in the chat
and then i'll uh i'll queue you up and
ask you to ask your question
and then you and bill can can engage in
that if you wouldn't like to
be um on youtube or like be on the
internets
asking your question you can just
indicate that when you write in the chat
and i can ask
it on your behalf other than that just
one at a time we'll see if we can get up
to some some interesting
insights here so uh i guess to start off
bill thanks for coming this is great uh
give your new book god bless the broken
bones coming out
and um i guess to just get us started if
you could just
run us through the main concept of of
that book and what you were trying to
achieve with it and what you think it
does
yeah first of all i want to say thank
you for having me on i really appreciate
the uh the offer the opportunity
i also just found out that you and i
have something else in common i'm a
massive ufc fan master of mma fan
i'm too old to do it now unless that's
all i saw in your book you're talking
about is great
yeah um yeah i just saw you know just
saw colby and tyrone go at it this past
weekend there's two
two belts on the line saturday for
anybody else who's uh interested in that
kind of thing
and adessanya versus costa should be
insane
so don't miss that one but anyway um as
far as
the silly things i do are concerned the
important stuff is mma let's talk about
this nonsense
i don't know if you read this god bless
the broken bones this is a
a journal of one year 365 daily entries
um and the the entries are motivated by
what i happen to have read that day
any news i happen to have encountered
that day
conversations i may have had so some of
the entries
are specifically about philosophy and
even more specifically about stoic
philosophy
others are about various injuries that i
suffer and
dealing with those others are about
interactions i've had at work or
interactions i've had outside of work
as i said items from the news so you get
a
year's worth of a journal from the
perspective of someone
who is uh practicing
stoicism slash cynicism and often
failing
often uh woefully inadequate i i am
woefully inadequate you can tell by
looking at me
so you know i i write down the struggles
uh i don't want to conceal anything i
don't want
to present myself to my reader as uh
something that i'm not uh i'm not i'm
not a stage not even close to it
i'm a guy who is um kind of grasping and
stumbling and occasionally i
i might uh stumble into the light for a
moment of clarity and uh hopefully
there's a few moments of clarity
in the book um this is my sixth book
i've got a seventh one another one
coming out uh next year this one
slave and sage this is directly about
stoicism remarks on the stoic handbook
of epictetus this comes out
next year in may but whether you want to
talk about that one or not
it's up to you entirely i hope i didn't
uh drone on too long just then
that's great okay not at all um and then
i guess to get us started because
obviously the two of us are really
familiar with stoicism and cynicism
but other people might not be so i don't
know maybe
like a quick 101 on stoicism and
cynicism and
maybe how they informed um your practice
in your journey in this book
sure historically the cynics came first
uh
whether antisthenes was the founder of
cynicism or whether it was diogenes or
one of the others as a
matter of some debate all of the
hellenistic schools
um try to trace their lineage back to
socrates for obvious reasons socrates
was a heroic
philosophical figure so the the
epicureans the stoics the cynics the
skeptics
uh they all claimed that they were
following the example of socrates living
life
as he lived it valuing what he valued
and of course
um they can't all be right um so the
cynics came first
um zeno the founder of stoicism
encountered the cynics and he
encountered cynic philosophy which was
uh largely about um
it was about the pursuit of virtue but
the fundamental idea
is that the only thing we should concern
ourselves with
is virtue gaining wisdom
becoming uh developing the other virtues
you know
courage justice fortitude
self-discipline
and all other social trappings were
nonsense
um diogenes famously coined the term
uh cosmopolitan by which he meant
contrary to what some commentators say
today
my view is what he meant was that he was
a
cosmopolitan means citizen of the cosmos
what he meant
was he was subject to the laws of the
cosmos we would call natural law
but he he had to obey the laws of nature
but as for the laws of man as for civil
law he he regarded those as nonsense the
social constructs were silly they
weren't to be taken seriously
and so he would do very uh taboo very
shocking things he would urinate in
public
he would allegedly masturbate in public
whether that's true or whether that's
something that was um presented by his
adversaries to sort of make him look bad
that's that's an open question
he would uh eat in places where it was
inappropriate to eat he would insult
people
um just for the sake of trying to wake
them up so
cynicism was very much a sort of
in-your-face
lifestyle that directly challenged
people to think about their values and
to think about how they were leading
their lives
when zeno encountered cynicism he
thought okay
uh these guys are on to something
diogenes cradies these people
they're right that virtue and wisdom
that's what we should care about
that's what's important uh our character
and the
um our efforts at self-rectification
and all the rest of the trappings are
kind of nonsensical however
you're not going to get a lot of
adherence you're not going to persuade a
lot of people
by urinating in public and by calling
them names and so on
so let's make a more palatable version
of cynicism
and from that this attempt to make it
more palatable
uh you know to make it the kind of thing
that the average citizen
might at least take seriously might
contemplate might consider
from that you get stoicism and um of
course after xeno
you get the the great stoics you get
mussonius rufus
you get seneca you get epictetus you get
marcus and
and on it goes again hope i didn't drown
on too long but
that's sort of the brief history of
where it comes from
yeah great and so one thing when i was
reading your book
that really struck me um as a stoic
someone who doesn't i don't identify as
much as a cynic
i saw so your summary there you know was
kind of cynicism as this
rougher stoicism or the stoicism that
that is kind of in a pure form that
hasn't been made palatable for the
the masses and what i was getting at
when i was reading your book was
i saw a real emphasis on hypocrisy um
and an emphasis on maybe social
convention
making people do things that doesn't
make doesn't make a lot of sense
um i guess if you could expand on that
in your book and how that relates to
cynicism in your view yeah my my
stoicism definitely shades towards
cynicism
uh diogenes is as as much of a hero to
me as
his epictetus um i i do
find there's something in me i have a
viscerally negative
reaction to being told that i i must say
x even if i do not believe x to be true
i must refrain from saying y even if i
think y
is true and is the correct way to
express myself the idea
that i should behave in ways that i find
to be either
ignoble or just silly or pointless
because
i'm expected to behave in this fashion
other people and their expectations
don't mean a great deal to me um anymore
than they did to diogenes
uh stoicism is sort of a decaffeinated
version of of cynicism and uh
i don't uh i don't really want to be any
more decaffeinated than i absolutely
have
to be i don't go out of my way well
i don't always go out of my way to uh
offend
people or irritate people but uh i i
don't overly concern myself with it
either i honestly don't even know
exactly
what this condition of being offended
amounts to
it's allegedly a psychological or
emotional state but anytime i
ask someone to describe to me what is
this condition of being offended i just
get synonyms
they say well i'm affronted i'm insulted
i'm agreed yeah those are synonyms
what is happening in your body and or
your consciousness
when you're offended and why should i
care why
should i concern myself with your mental
states i i can't control your mental
states
uh i don't ask anyone to concern
themselves with mine
i've never in my life said i'm offended
uh other than you know to illustrate the
fact
i don't know what it means so um
yeah i mean i'm i'm a cynic
cynical stoic or a stoical cynic or
whatever
yeah cool um so
when i was taking a look at the book
it's structured as you said as like a
journal
and so there's kind of an essay for
every day and one thing you talk about
in the introduction is that it's this
process of like sustained attention or
reflection
um so you're gonna you know think about
your life think about what you're
encountering
actively and write about it so i mean
maybe if you could describe that process
or what you learned
differently in that year or how that's
how that year went differently than a
year that was maybe less reflective
right um i think the first thing
well by the first thing one of the one
of the things i realized early on
is how often i found myself um
behaving in a particular fashion because
of expectations other person's
expectations or what i believe their
expectations to be
rather than just saying what i was
inclined to say doing what i was
inclined to do um
how often i was uh i was presenting to
other people a persona
rather than the actual person that is me
and i began to wonder
how often do i do this how often do all
of us do this
and when you start asking how often do
we behave this way and then you watch
for example
politicians or you watch celebrities
you realize right away that for them
it's it's virtually
24 hours a day certainly every time
they're on camera certainly every time
they've got a
microphone in their face they're saying
things that they don't really believe to
be true
or they're saying things they believe
but they're saying them in a way that is
very
unnatural very stilted very
artificial and you realize it's not just
people who are on tv
um it's just about everybody i mean
we're all constantly censoring ourselves
we're all
constantly um i don't know
sort of governing governing what we say
and do in ways i
i think are not particularly healthy and
certainly are not
necessary um or at least i don't
no one has convinced me that they are
necessary
now you know i'm not suggesting that all
um all forms of manners all forms of
behavioral norms are to be jettisoned or
something
i'm not going to go to a funeral and
start shouting curses
or insulting the dead person i'm not
gonna do that
um there are things there are terms we
should not use because they've
always only been used in uh indefensible
fashion
there are a lot there are you know um
expressions of that nature but not
nearly as many as we're being
uh as we're being told today there's
just a political correctness in my view
has just
uh gone utterly insane um
far far too many the speech police are
everywhere and they
are far too influential for my tastes so
that's one of the first things i notice
is geez i'm awfully guarded
and i'm i think i'm probably a lot less
guarded than most people are and i
notice how guarded i am
i started to wonder about how how much
we're just sort of
pretending to each other how much we're
you know pretending to be people that we
really aren't
and what would be the advice for getting
rid of the persona
or beginning to like engage in this
process of
being less guarded or more truthful
i would say you have to start with
really brutal
brutally honest introspection
when you are when you are watching what
you say when you are
behaving as someone else wants you to
behave you're typically aware of it
sometimes we gloss over that aspect of
our experience
where we're focused on others and on
what uh
we think they want to hear from us but
if you if you take a moment either when
it's happening
or after it has happened to intro
respect and ask wait
was that me that i was presenting to
this other person or was that just the
decaffeinated version of myself the more
palatable
version of myself that i was presenting
um
i don't know how often most people are
brutally honest
with that kind of introspection brutally
honest with their assessment of
who they really are um we are after all
we are a species of talking ape right
i mean we are we are
descended from uh
murderers and rapists and all sorts of
people who survived long enough to
procreate back before there were laws
and i suspect that surviving long enough
to procreate was largely a matter of
doing doing things that are uh for very
good reason anathema today
we're we're descended from beasts we're
descended from scavengers we're
descended from
a predatory uh predatory set of
ancestors
we can't possibly be as pristine as we
often make ourselves out
to be today at least i know i'm not
so yeah um
and then so there's this idea of
beginning with radical
honesty and and introspection um
and so one thing you say in the
introduction is like you know
the the author i'm paraphrasing but it's
like the author of this book has
problems
yeah you know if you relate to the book
you probably have problems too
right um or relate entirely at least and
so i guess is part of that process
also looking at the parts of yourself
you don't like or where is the
where do you build that up with like
self-improvement or like pumping
yourself up versus
well it's difficult to improve oneself
if you will not be honest about your
flaws and your backup
pillows and the places where you need
improvement right and uh
that line in the introduction was semi
tongue-in-cheek but but only semi uh
i i do have problems i do need help um
i am sometimes an obnoxious jerk uh
i am sometimes needlessly abrasive um
and that does come out in the book i i
don't want to conceal myself from my
reader
so there are lots of entries in the book
in which i
take myself to task i say you know what
a pathetic weakling you were today
and i described some you know some
occasion on which i i let an injury
slow me down or i like the fact i didn't
sleep so well slow me down
or i found myself worrying about had i
contracted a cold or had i contracted
the flu
if you think about how pathetic that is
when you look at the common lot
of humanity even today right most people
on planet earth live on the
equivalent of two american dollars a day
uh
you know think about people who are
facing real oppression not first world
oppression but real oppression where
they might be murdered at any moment
uh you know you look at people living in
uh the developing world and
what they have to deal with and i'm i'm
gonna be
forestalled by i'm gonna be uh slowed
down by the fact that i might have a
cold
or maybe my my back is hurting me a
little bit you see
um military vets coming home from war
missing limbs
right or having been hideously burned or
having ptsd
so intense that you know every snap of a
twig
sends them into this intense fight or
flight response and oh
i'm gonna [ __ ] and moan about the fact
that my my 52 year old back is a little
tense
today i just that kind of weakness i
always find pathetic
and it's even more troubling when it's
my weakness and
i'm being pathetic so i call myself on
the carpet
um repeatedly throughout the year for
doing
things like that and other other stupid
things just making stupid mistakes
you know it's not a it's not a laudatory
book
regarding its author it's not me saying
hey look at
look at how cool i am it's like it's me
saying look at what a wreck i am are you
anything like me
do you need as much help as i do uh it's
that's the approach um
it reminds me of epictetus but you're
kind of like um
doing that to yourself and helping along
that process
um and then i guess i have one more
question and then i know peter has a
question so we'll pass it off to him
um i guess the question is how you frame
the book so i was reading it i was
wondering like
is this do you view this as
as like arts do you view this as a
self-help book for other people is this
a philosophical project that you engaged
in for yourself
that you then might think inspires or
helps other people i guess how do you
how do you frame the mod
my approach was what i regard as the
approach that marcus aurelius took
writing the meditations
then i'm not comparing myself to marcus
aurelius he's a far greater man than me
and far
wiser just the approach um i'm writing
down these thoughts in the initial
instance in the first instance for my
benefit
i i'm thinking about myself my flaws
various ways i should improve
the surrounding circumstances i
encounter
however uh there are commonalities to
the human experience we all we're all
flawed uh we are all sinners if you want
to use that kind of language we are all
uh faced with a world that is very large
and powerful and we are frail and
ephemeral we don't last very long
so if these reflections can be
beneficial to
me and i believe they were my hope is
that they might also be beneficial to
others um anyone from whom i've gotten
any feedback about the book
the feedback has been interestingly
uniform in one way everyone has said
there were times when i was reading this
when i laughed out loud there were other
times when i was reading this that i
found myself
giving being the book the finger
and there are other times when i found
myself not really understanding
what the point of this was where i felt
kind of lost
um and that's because i
sometimes felt kind of lost and i was
writing down my thoughts about the fact
that
i'm a bit lost here i'm not sure what
i'm not sure
what the wise response to these
circumstances is and i
don't know how to be virtuous in this
particular case um
so it's a self-help book
that starts inside here and hopefully
you know
moves um to a more generalizable
um perspective
great i think i think there's a lot of
value
to seeing that process take place too
and not just
and also you're like seems to me you
have this idea of radical
honesty and you don't want to you know
pretend like you're the sage or perfect
or anything like that
so part of it is is this acknowledgment
of being lost
that that makes a lot of sense to me um
i guess i'll start pass it on to the
chat room so we can get a discussion
going so peter did you want to start us
off
yeah uh so i have uh i have actually
three questions maybe i'll just ask
one or two um so i've been journaling to
myself every day since kovit came online
and i've been doing it like maybe 150
days now as people
still know and i found it uh is
transformational and i've been doing it
publicly too so i've been like just
releasing on my mailing list and stuff
like that
and you know it's it's like you it's
based off marcus aurelius's journaling
practice
um so it's to myself technically but i
know
people are going to read this right away
like the night when i when i release it
and so there's that dynamic of that kind
of impression management that's just
bubbling up all the time
and then kind of the what is really for
or at least what at the pretense of its
forwards to kind of that self-reflection
transformation
so i wonder how you wrestled with that
when you're writing it i'm assuming
knowing you were going to release this
as a book
yeah it's interesting the the first one
i wrote my second book but the first
book of this nature i wrote was this one
meditations on self discipline and
failure stoic exercise mental fitness
this one i did not know i was going to
release
i was just doing what marcus aurelius
did i was just
um writing the journal for my own
benefit
um i have an anxiety and depression
disorder that i
apparently inherited from my dad so i
often struggle with those kind of
challenges and i i found that
you know bibliotherapy or journaling was
a very
effective technique for getting my mind
back under control
but after a while i realized i bet there
are a lot of people who who might
benefit from this i bet there are a lot
of people who face these same challenges
and uh because i was reading it to
myself i wrote in second person
right everything says you did the
following today and you made this
mistake
um so and i've i've maintained that
practice with every book except for
this one the only one that's not written
in second person is
alive for living this is just a
collection
of articles that i've published in
academic journals over the past 20 years
and i did some research on that and
found out that most academic articles
are
are read by grand total of seven people
so
what's the point i decided to go ahead
and put them into a form that was more
accessible
because i write in second person i think
some readers
are a little bit um they find it a
little bit abrasive
especially when i'm criticizing myself
if i say if i write something like
you pathetic weakling here's what you
did today
well when you're reading that when you
read the words you pathetic weakling you
say what me you're calling me weekly no
i'm calling me a weekly i'm just
wondering uh if
other people might um have the same kind
of concerns about themselves about their
character
so uh everything i've done
is a long winded answer question
everything i've written over the past
few years
has been in the first instance an
attempt at
self-help literal self-help trying to
help this guy right here
and i hope it generalizes
to be self-help for others as well
that's the idea i
hope i answered your question yeah and
so i have uh
two more questions i'll just sneak in
both in right now and feel free to field
which one resonates more
um so we talk a lot here at the store
about like an ecology what john ray
called oncology of practices
uh we have like a wisdom gym that's
forming uh so basically
don't just be relying on one life
practice or spiritual practice you have
to have like a balance of a bunch of
them in your ecology
and uh and like as as michael
and you know like the modern stoic
community there's no consensus of like
wow the stoics actually practice how you
should practice we all have our own
bespoke ecology
michael like uses jiu jitsu as a form of
stoic practice
so i'm curious besides the journaling
aspect what is your ecology of practice
that's one question and then the other
question is about the culture war
uh because you're an open trump
supporter in california
um and as i imagine you get uh um
comments here or there oh yeah
and and i would argue you might disagree
with this but i argue like across the
political spectrum people get
emotionally triggered
especially when they feel like they've
been characterized wrongly
so do you when that occurs to you those
cultural dynamics
how do you internally emotionally
respond to it okay
uh the first part of your question is
about other story practices besides
journaling besides writing uh i engage
in the uh the practice of pre-meditation
malorum that is consider all of the
sort of worst case scenarios all of the
seemingly
unpleasant or disastrous possibilities
that could befall you
so for example back when i was driving
to work
i'm teaching online now because of code
um
i'm a terrible driver because i'm a
terrible driver i often find myself in
these circumstances that
that could be really frustrating or have
to slam on the brakes or
someone you know either i inadvertently
cut someone off or someone cuts me off
before i would get in the car i would
uh consciously think okay you're gonna
be commuting it's about a 25 minute
commute
you don't like driving you're not good
at it
often when you're driving other people
irritate you and
you often irritate other people so
gird your loins now prepare yourself now
so that if something comes up
you won't immediately be thrown into
anger and frustration
you'll be able to be on that first
instant when you slam on the brakes the
first image is just
but then think okay all right getting
angry getting frustrated that's not
gonna do me any good
not gonna not gonna help it's not gonna
cause the traffic to dissipate right
so i would sort of remind myself in
advance
of the various things that could go
wrong so that i can respond more
rationally when they do
just one example i also do the uh the
review of the day uh before bed
what did i do well today what did i do
poorly today
um what did i what did i not even
encounter today that i
anticipated our expectations are another
thing
we can work on governing right um
i mean consider this this uh this
interaction
right if i came into this thinking oh
i'm gonna be on the uh
the stoa podcast and now my book's going
to be a bestseller because everyone's
going to read that would be an
irrational expectation not you know if
you guys are cool and i you know i like
your show and everything
it's totally not going to be a rationale
let me say this okay
all right i'll take your word for it
uh the second part of your uh question
uh yeah being a being a trump supporter
being a conservative and i'm i'm a
pretty hardcore conservative
i'm a far right wing not job um
out here in california and especially
being
an academic uh i think i joked earlier
that i'm one of three conservatives
at my my college that's that's not an
exaggeration
we actually had an interaction online
over email
the other day actually last week and i
said okay look
if you don't think we have an
ideological monoculture
here at delta college let me issue you
this challenge and i said look i
dr william fariolo and a conservative
and a trump supporter
i hereby ask all of the other faculty
full part-time everybody
who agree with me who are also
conservatives and trump supporters to
respond to this email and say so in
public
one person responded one other person
said i'm a conservative i said i voted
for trump i don't really like him it's
just that i
really didn't like hillary and i'm
pro-life like so don't give me
a hard time by being a trump supporter
it was this very sort of muted
uh expression of conservatism i got
eight emails
from people who said bill i'm a
conservative i voted for trump but for
god's sake don't
tell anybody no matter what you don't
tell anybody because they know
that um their job will immediately be in
jeopardy
uh these were mostly untenured people
and they they know that if they came out
as
uh open trump supporters they would
there's no chance of them ever being
tenured
i can tell you that i've been on i've
been here for almost 25 years i've
been on many selection committees uh
someone who's openly conservative in an
interview
not a chance in the world of getting
hired no chance and
the part-time people they all said well
if they know i voted for trump
they'll just never give me any more
courses the equivalent of getting fired
and uh i responded the same way i said i
i understand entirely and you're right
don't worry
i won't tell on you so um yeah i get an
enormous
amount of flack for being trump a
supporter um if you voted for trump you
are of course
a racist a sexist a xenophobe an
islamophobe of a homophobe
and of course i'm not actually any of
those things but that is the
immediate presumption um stoicism comes
in handy
right being emotionally detached from
being called those kinds of things and
being labeled in that way and
being psychologically able to
psychologically distance myself from
these uh attitudes that people have
about me
it certainly comes in handy and i'm
certainly
much better able to deal with that now
than i would have been say
15 or 20 years ago before i really got
into the practice
of stoicism cool thanks
does that answer your question or yep
right
by the way if you want to uh like you
know listen to me for being trump
supporter and like you know
call me stuff feel free to go right
ahead i won't get offended
that's that's the that's the after party
we will do that okay all right
fair enough by the way he's going to win
a landslide again
so just if you're betting anybody going
to bedding websites
it's going to be a 321 electoral college
votes for trump
guaranteed
um that feels like bait it feels like
you're trying
um manny you had a question did you want
to ask
uh bill yes thank you
i voted for trump too but
i don't really like labels i'm not
anything i just
i did the thing um so i'm wondering
how have you freed yourself and or
where have you refocused your energy
during the course of this
rigorous self-reflection i do
self-reflect but
not such a measured daily way for such a
long period of time and i'm thinking
about how the energy that it takes to
put on a persona the energy that it
takes to
be offended like if you've recovered
that energy like where have you
redirected it actually that's a really
interesting
question and it is true um i have much
more energy
now that i'm just not subjecting myself
to
being angry and getting upset about what
people think
i sleep better i my digestion is better
you know um it's it's a much healthier
way to engage with other people and with
reality
uh i uh i direct the energy in a couple
of
different places i um i started learning
how to cook
about four years back and now i actually
do most of the cooking
at the time my wife was working long
hours and i i wasn't working
quite as much or a lot of my work was at
home so i figured that wasn't fair i
would start taking up
the burden of cooking and i found i
really enjoyed cooking
i work out a lot i'm getting old but i
still try to
try to work out you know five days a
week or so
a lot of yard work a lot of sort of
physical exercise to
literally burn up calories and burn up
energy and i write a lot i mean i've
written
um what is it five books in the past two
years or something like that
so i try to keep the mind busy i try to
keep
this rapidly decaying carcass that i
call myself
uh i try and keep it from decaying more
rapidly than it has to
and um you know i uh i
turn beef and chicken into uh edible
meals they're mostly edible no one's
don't died yet
that sounds kind of a quotidian sort of
banal answer but that that really is
true it's a
i work out i cook and i write that's
you know how i spend most of my free
time
yeah and improved sleep and improved
digestion that's
that's important stuff oh yeah
absolutely
um anxiety and depression are not
they're psychosomatic disorders they're
not just psychological disorders
i used to have a terrible problem
sleeping i always had
really serious digestive problems um
i had lots of nagging aches and pains
because i was always
tense i was always stressed i still have
that stuff but it's all maybe
25 percent of what it used to be maybe
even
maybe even lower than that
thanks for the question yeah thank you
uh maybe did you want to ask your
question
yeah sure hey will thanks for
uh hosting a session um what what i'm
curious about is i i get this like
feeling when you talk about like how
much harder
it is for just any other person than it
is for
for you you know whoever you are and in
in that moment i get that feeling of
like oh yeah like there's a shift in
perspective that goes along with that i
feel like more energetic i feel less
bogged down by being stuck in my head
but sometimes
when i'm on my own and i hear myself say
those things like you're a pathetic
weakling
i i do not get the same shift in
perspective i feel more weighed down
i feel like it's like mere self-abuse
and it's not
giving me that shift in perspective that
would make it constructive
and so i wonder if you have any advice
for for somebody who would like
that shift in perspective but sometimes
isn't finding that the tools are
delivering that
absolutely and in the beginning i had
the same problem it just felt like
self-abuse it really was just self-abuse
it was you're pathetic
you're stupid you're weak you're a loser
if that's where it stops
that is just self-abuse and you're just
going to suffer if you
if it if it motivates states change
so you can actually be proud of yourself
or feel better about yourself for having
overcome
one of your frailties one of your flaws
if it's
instead of saying you're pathetic and
weak say hold on
you're being pathetic and weak right now
and you don't have to be
right why don't you try this alternative
here's a simple example
um i was cleaning up the garage a couple
weeks ago and i
had to move some heavy stuff and my back
has always bothered me i have had my
neck reconstructed so
i always have back problems so i wanted
to pick up this box
and it was bulky and heavy and i went to
pick it up and i got this shooting pain
right down the middle of my back
so i put it down uh it was kind of an
involuntary i kind of dropped it
and i thought well this has to get done
my wife is
five feet tall and she wasn't there at
the time anyway this has to get done so
i said look
look you're being a wimp you're being
weak
you don't let yourself be convinced that
you can't
move this box you can move this box you
can do what needs to be done it's gonna
hurt
but it's not as if it's impossible now
pick it up
move it accept the pain and when you're
done
you will have done something worth doing
and sure enough i picked it up got the
same shooting pain
moved the box cracked my back went back
inside
and when my wife got home and said did
you clean up the garage i said yeah i
actually uh
you know i got everything where you
needed it so you can you can put your
car in the garage now
so i had accomplished a goal that
benefited my wife a person i love more
than anyone else in the world
by overcoming the initial reticence the
initial
sort of physiological reluctance to do
this thing
so if you don't want to you know
use abusive talk with yourself you don't
have to i say
get to the point where you can move
forward and accomplish
goals and and make something positive
happen for me
i'm an italian guy from jersey so it
doesn't bother me to call myself names i
i grew up i was the youngest of three
boys i got the crap
kicked out of me every day i got i was
always being called stuff just just
doesn't bother me anymore
um you can take a different approach
instead of saying you're a pathetic
loser you can say oh come on now
come on now you can do better than this
right maybe that's a
more viable approach for other people
does that help
yeah absolutely thank you so much sure
great so let's pass it on to uh elliott
now if you want to ask your question
is elliot still there hey oh there we go
hey
so um so i appreciate
your um i guess not being too precious
about your own experience and and not
taking to
taking yourself too seriously i really
admire that
um but when you talk about i guess the
cynical side of
you know um what what came off as like
you know
to hell with conventions and norms
and all that i'm wondering you know and
this is something
i'm sitting with in general like the uh
the the balance between the individual
and their
personal pursuit of personal development
and and how we kind of form
a healthy society in general and i'm
wondering
how if everyone just issues
social norms or um
you know not all uh rules or guidelines
that are in place are there to control
us
some are there out of wisdom like you
know millions of years or
thousands of years of wisdom that's kind
of been passed on through cultures
so i'm wondering how you know how would
you design
a healthy society incorporating your
philosophy and approach but still
you know and i guess not to throw too
much into your your
uh put words in your mouth but like you
know how would you create a healthy
society
in light of um having that that
uh aversion to social norms
right before i answer your question has
anyone ever told you that you look a lot
like greg jackson
one of the top mma trainers at jackson
winkle johnny trained jon jones and
there's this really cool you know he
used to train gsp back when gsp was
champ
there's this really cool really stoic
slash cynic moment
where gsp was fighting josh kashak and
he comes back to his corner
and he says i think i tore my abductor
and greg jackson looks at me says oh so
you want to quit and give up the title
and jsp looks hard if i said no he said
then don't tell me about it again i want
to hear about it
right we're fighting we'll take you to
hospital later um
so just just made me think of that at
that moment um
yes i'm sorry he's a very handsome man
you're right
yeah absolutely yeah handsome devil no
doubt about it um
as for building a healthy society or a
you know a better society
i am not convinced i have no idea how to
do it
no idea i'm not convinced that it can be
done given
uh current circumstances especially
i tend to think in the first instance
about the united states i live here
330 million people it's not clear to me
that we even agree about the most
fundamental values anymore
um we have become balkanized sort of
morally balkanized we have become
ideologically balkanized
i am not optimistic about
the united states enjoying a cohesive
future
perhaps it can be done i am betting on
i don't want to say collapse and
dissolution um
i don't i don't know that the united
states
as a unified entity lasts another 25
years
there'll be a place called the united
states of america but
uh whether or not it will be in
practical terms
one unified nation as it was
you know say 40 years ago i
i don't know i don't have the answer to
that and
i would argue it's unhealthy to worry
about that
right i can't make it happen i i can't
conjure a healthy well-functioning
streamlined nation into being uh
it's hard enough for me to keep myself
well functioning and streamlined and
pursuing virtue and wisdom
um i think that
uh overly intense concern about
sociopolitical matters
is psychologically emotionally unhealthy
um
look at what happened to half the
country after the last election
man you can just just go to youtube and
type in
reaction to trump election 2016. you see
people
weeping wailing gnashing their teeth and
throwing bricks through windows
obviously we have riots going on in
every major city in the nation right now
um if that's a manifestation of concern
about
socio-political issues i say maybe be
less concerned
um work on yourself work on
conducting yourself in virtuous fashion
now clearly if everyone did that
we would have a a better nation but
you see the idea that everyone's going
to do that or even a majority is going
to do that
is not plausible in my view
so i don't worry about um those kinds of
broad scale issues
right so my my brief answer how do we do
this i have no idea and i
doubt it can be done that's that's the
honest answer it's not satisfying but
i'm accustomed to leaving people
unsatisfied i'm married you know
if i saw it that way i'd probably vote
for trump too
so do you have kids or are you thinking
of having kids is that
i have three stepchildren so i guess
that would be the way i'd
i'd transfer the question like how do
you you know raise them even in a
household where they have to kind of
live and coexist together um where do
you find that like just be independent
and do whatever you want
versus no i'm i mean
okay i'm sorry i would never say do
whatever you want um not if whatever you
want me is acting on impulse in an art
you know our best deal instincts that's
that's not being virtuous i encourage my
children
to um develop their intellect i
encourage them to develop
uh the various virtues to be courageous
to be
uh self-disciplined or temperate to be
just to be fair dealing with others and
with themselves to be honest
i think honesty um is one of the um
one of the sort of central concerns that
is either falling into disfavors being
radically misunderstood these days
so i always encourage my children to be
morally decent persons um
none of my kids could possibly ever get
the impression that i think it's okay
for them to steal or i think it's okay
for them to
mistreat a woman or that it's okay for
them to
mistreat a weaker person
or that it's okay to you know lie for
some kind of material benefit
um so i i advise people to
conduct themselves in virtuous fashion
uh myself included
as for expecting others to do so
that's a that's a losing it's a losing
gambit
you can't expect the public at large to
be virtuous it's
the best my knowledge never happened so
i don't expect it
thank you sorry i was just cooking so
that's okay hey i like cooking
thanks elliot um we have a question from
theodore which is kind of related to
this so that's a good
follow-up hey
hey thank you okay how are you i'm doing
pretty well
uh so yeah i'm a cynic as well so i
relate to
what you're saying a lot but like that's
why this question is so interesting
so as aesthetic and realizing that
the human species has been here however
long and has gone through way
more tumultuous times than this are you
a trump supporter
like to kind of be a heel
to attract negative fives
no not at all um i i don't really
understand most of the complaints about
trump i don't
see the evidence for some of these
complaints um
maybe i have a blind spot maybe i just i
just don't perceive the alleged problems
i mean look i understand he's boorish
i understand if you look at the totality
of his life you know he's almost
certainly an adulterer he's almost
certainly
you know probably engaged in dirty
business deals it's hard to become a
billionaire without you know cutting
corners here and there
but i just don't see the man as the
monster that some people make him out to
be
um my primary look i i supported trump
for two
fundamental reasons one is hillary
clinton and the democratic party
i i share no values with him nothing
none um secondly i regarded him as the
much more pro-life
candidate which is an important issue to
me i don't believe
we should encourage um
i don't even think we should allow but
much less encourage the slaughter of
unborn human beings in the womb
and i knew he was close to being
pro-life than she would be able to
appoint supreme court justices that were
more pro-life
and would hopefully eventually overturn
the
ludicrous decision that his roe v wade
and finally
i am concerned about uh immigration
restrictionism and as soon as you say
that people say ah
racism i don't care where they're coming
from i don't care where i don't care if
immigrants are coming from
you know uh asia africa
europe i don't care to come from canada
we've got 330 million people
it is impossible in my view to maintain
a cohesive culture where we all
share a sort of rudimentary set of base
level
values if we have no criteria about
whom we allow in um
i i think there's this there's a strange
kind of
globalist cosmopolitan idea that if you
cross a border you take an oath
you become uh interchangeable with any
member of that society
all right here's a simple analogy as far
as i've never heard anyone complain
about the amish
i've never heard anyone say well the
amish they're terrible people because
they don't want
us living with them but they don't want
us living with them
and i don't blame them right the amish
don't want me
moving into their community because i
don't share their values i don't share
their traditions i don't share their
history i'm not quote one of them
and i probably can't learn to become one
maybe i could but probably not
if you have a community of say a
thousand amish people
and a hundred people like me move in
that community's been destroyed
it will never be what it once was now
if you find what it once was to be
objectionable you might say well good
they shouldn't have been that way
but i can understand why the amish want
to be separate they want they want to
have
a community of people who understand
each other
i think on a broader scale it's very
difficult
to maintain the health of the nation if
you don't have a community of people
who in some fundamental underlying
fashion understand one each other one
another and
share some basic facets of a world view
and just can't maintain that with open
borders or de facto open doors in my
view it can't be done
um and well uh
i point to the current situation
has at least partial inductive evidence
in support of my view
um it's chaos out there it's
people are literally shooting each other
literally at each other's throats
um well so i'll add to that
so you said trump will win in a
landslide and yeah i don't have a dog in
either fight because
i'm a bit more cynical than you even but
uh you said he'd win in a landslide but
you still think that the country
itself won't exist in 50 60 years so
even if
your views come to fruition
does it just delay things
right i i think i think at most it
delays
the the slide the collapse the uh
the slouching toward gamora it delays it
by maybe i don't know
a couple of years i think we're doomed
either way
so if biden were elected it sooner
but yet doomed the question is who will
take us to hell at a slightly slower
rate of speed
i think trump gets us to hell a little
bit later than biden gets us there but
we're going to help if you look around
you say why am i in this hand basket
that's where we're headed um i don't
think there's any way to stop it i hope
i'm wrong
um i also don't really have a dog in the
fight like if i'm wrong if trump loses
i'm not going to weep well and hash my
teeth i'm not going to go throw bricks
through windows
i'll just say oh i guess i misread that
one
um i i'm not i try not to be emotionally
invested
in the outcome of an election because i
have no power i live in california
my vote is that be phenomenal let me let
you know secret biden's going to win
california
no matter what i do or don't do a
budget's going to win california
just like no matter what anybody does
trump is going to win
you know idaho there are certain things
that are not
plausibly malleable or subject to our
even our influence much less our control
so i'm not gonna worry about it but um
it's a preferred indifferent for me that
trump wins rather than biden it doesn't
happen
yeah life goes on
did i answer your question i mean i no
no yeah you answered it perfectly
no i'm not trying to be a troll or
anything i actually think
trump is a better person for the job but
that's not saying much
um thank you so we have time for one
more question from alex
um and i'll read this one so how do you
resolve the tension
uh between supporting honesty and
supporting a president who lies
is is how the question is goes all
presidents lie
all presence lie pathologically uh of
course trump lies
of course biden lies of course hillary
lies of course you know
w bush lies um if you're gonna vote for
a president who never lies uh you're not
gonna vote
right there's there's no such thing as
politicians who don't lie and
i i challenge anyone to present me uh
you know
an example of the contrary the question
is not
how can you vote for this for a liar
it's which liar do you prefer
and whose lives are less deleterious to
the culture at large
whose lives i see trump lying more out
of a sense of self-aggrandizement
trump is he's very thin skinned he's in
some ways kind of immature
i don't perceive him lying about
broad-scale issues that actually affect
the health and well-being
of the nation right now you might
as a as an example of the country you
might say well he lied about covet
i i would say he he's he tried
to avoid panic about covet in the
process of doing that
yeah he did not exactly tell the whole
truth but
i don't know that it would have been
better for him to say okay listen
we've got a plague on our hands
according to
initial cdc estimates this thing is
probably going to kill two to three
million americans
just wanted to let you know that it's
very highly communicable and
millions of you are going to die but
don't worry we'll be okay after that
i don't believe that's wise leadership
right
i i don't mind the way he handled it
down playing it as he puts it
i think you know when
when fdr told told the public
we have nothing to fear but fear itself
that wasn't true
it's never true that we have nothing of
fear but fear itself right
there was a an economic crisis there was
a brewing uh
full-scale world war in the offing
but you don't say imagine the president
said look look
our economy is in the tank we're heading
into a world war
that we almost certainly can't afford
and we're going to lose hundreds of
thousands of people
and we don't even know if we're going to
win the nazis might win this thing the
axis nations might win this thing
and our nation could very well be
destroyed as a result
of this um of this conflict
but don't worry but we'll do our best
that's
that's not leadership so yeah trump lies
they all lie
his lies don't bother me any more than
biden's lies uh by i mean there's anyone
out there claiming biden is not
a compulsive pathological liar the guy
who literally lifted one of his speeches
from a british politician from decades
ago
the idea claims he never spoke to hunter
biden about his
uh work at burisma and in china um
the guy who just said the other day that
there is no supreme court session
between now and the election
uh now he might be so senile he doesn't
know that the supreme court starts the
first monday in october
maybe that wasn't a lie maybe he's just
lost it but
certainly an untrue statement and he's
made lots and lots of others
200 million americans will die by the
time i finish this talk
i assume he meant 200 000 but you know
he's a liar trump's a liar um
my business is for me not to be a liar
that's what i concern myself with
whether anybody else is is really not my
business
thanks bill um well going to pass it off
to peter to
to wrap up the session um cool
cool yeah um anything you would like to
leave us off with uh bill like
things we can uh where we can find you
what not
well i don't know why anybody would want
to find me um i'm not that interesting
if you want to find my books
go to uh amazon you know they're taking
over the world
it's interesting how they're none of the
rioters have attacked any amazon plants
isn't that
fascinating they like to burn down small
businesses they don't like to burn down
amazon or apple or ibm
i don't think that's a coincidence but
anyway off topic there
you can go to amazon you can go to
barnes and noble you can go to the john
hunt publishing website
you can order my books there if you want
my books uh
if after hearing me and you know sort of
making my cyber acquaintance you want
nothing further to do with me that's
that's cool too i'll be fine um apart
from that
i do exist in physical reality uh please
don't come here and burn my house down
but if you want to just talk
i'm in lodi um there's no reason to be
particularly interested in me though
uh i recommend reading the other stoics
the other contemporaries who are writing
about stoicism
john sellers massimo piliucci donald
robertson
um chakrapani there are a whole bunch of
guys are putting out good stuff um
the guy who just wrote the practical
stoic his name is ward
if friends or something friend's award
or something
yeah he might be coming onto the stoa um
i was missing them to mike
the title of the book is the uh the
practicing stoic right that's right
look for that one that's a good one
there's lots of good stuff out there
don't just read me
no one else is reading me so you know
why should
the people watching this do it i like
this anti-marketing strategy
um all right so i'll make some
announcements in a moment but
uh bill thank you so much for coming to
stowa today uh
mike thanks so much for emceeing um so
upcoming events
we have well once we have a bunch coming
up one tomorrow peter wang as a sense
maker of residence this is the last
session
he's talking about the mental models he
uses to navigate the complexity of
life um and then on saturday we have
michael ashcroft
coming in uh he's a certified alexander
practitioner in the alexander technique
and so that's at 12 p.m eastern time the
alexander technique is you know getting
kind of an awareness of
your your body habits and your postures
and how that affects you
so that's that's right the feldenkrais
technique is that
like an offshoot of it i think so maybe
maybe it looks like she says yes to that
um yes that'd be cool so if you want to
check that out uh bill that's that
you can rsvp there's on the website the
store.ca we've got tons of events coming
up if you like to support us on patreon
you can do us all right there
yeah so everyone thank you for coming up
today
thank you for uh for inviting me to